<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on k7jsx.net</title>
    <link>https://k7jsx.net/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on k7jsx.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 14:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://k7jsx.net/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Field Day 2025</title>
      <link>https://k7jsx.net/posts/field-day-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 14:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://k7jsx.net/posts/field-day-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2025 marks the second year I plan to participate in Field Day. &lt;br&gt;
The ARRL describes Field Day as&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Field Day is ham radio&amp;rsquo;s open house. Every June, more than 40,000 hams throughout North America set up temporary transmitting stations in public places to demonstrate ham radio&amp;rsquo;s science, skill, and service to our communities and our nation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, some aspects of this this description are &lt;em&gt;aspirational&lt;/em&gt;.
My experience with the &amp;ldquo;open house&amp;rdquo; aspects are a mixed bag but I can identify
with need to showcase the &amp;ldquo;science, skill and service&amp;rdquo; Amateur Radio Ops can provide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;2025 marks the second year I plan to participate in Field Day. &lt;br&gt;
The ARRL describes Field Day as&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Field Day is ham radio&amp;rsquo;s open house. Every June, more than 40,000 hams throughout North America set up temporary transmitting stations in public places to demonstrate ham radio&amp;rsquo;s science, skill, and service to our communities and our nation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, some aspects of this this description are &lt;em&gt;aspirational&lt;/em&gt;.
My experience with the &amp;ldquo;open house&amp;rdquo; aspects are a mixed bag but I can identify
with need to showcase the &amp;ldquo;science, skill and service&amp;rdquo; Amateur Radio Ops can provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-backstory&#34;&gt;Some backstory&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2024&lt;/strong&gt; was my first year as a General and operating in Field Day was a contributing force
behind earning my upgrade. Consequently, it was also a proof of concept for my portable operating.
Using a homebrew end-fed antenna, fishing pole used as a mast and an IC-705 I was able to
make contacts across the nation. It was the first time I was able to experience 20 meters
during contest conditions and I barely knew what I was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interaction between a few hams that day would set the tone for Field Day going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Station Calling CQ: &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;CQ Field Day. This is ***** calling CQ Field Day.&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Unknown Second Station: &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;Frequency is in use old man!!&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Unknown Third Station: &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;It&#39;s Field Day! Every frequency is in use!&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the rhetoric I&amp;rsquo;d heard about proper operating procedures seemingly
tossed out in the presence of a not-a-contest contest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2025&#34;&gt;2025&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the lessons learned from last years event and 13
completed Parks on the Air activations I would undoubtedly be more prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few goals for this year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operate multiple bands. (Last year was just 20 and 10 meters.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operate multiple transmitters.  (Last year was just a single TX.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple antenna types. (wire and vertical.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work 17 and 80 meters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QRP!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goals in mind and fellow operator &lt;code&gt;N7DEV&lt;/code&gt; in tow we headed to Mt. Charleston to
escape the Southern Nevada heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;station-configurations&#34;&gt;Station Configurations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First order of business was to get the first station online. &lt;code&gt;N7DEV&lt;/code&gt; will
be operating 10 meters. Original idea was to run the Chameleon CHA-BV but I quickly
realized I could not get that into tune on 10. 20 and 17 were fine but the SWR would
quickly climb to over 4 when adjusted near 28400khz. Later I would consult the manual
and learn I needed to shorten the radials to achieve 10 meters but in the moment
it was time to fall back to the second antenna option, an EFHW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wire was in the air! Progress! Now let&amp;rsquo;s see if the band is alive. Bringing up the
waterfall display revealed no signals across the entire Technician portion of the band.
Nothing to worry about yet as the event hadn&amp;rsquo;t officially begun yet.
Leaving &lt;code&gt;N7DEV&lt;/code&gt; with some tips to familiarize himself with the IC-705 I moved on to
set up my operating position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be operating the Elecraft Kx2 and a 35.5&amp;rsquo; random wire from the bed of my truck.
This trusty combo has served me well for multiple POTA activations.
The receiver, parametric mic eq and voice keyer really are the showpieces in the Kx2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;working-out-the-bugs&#34;&gt;Working out the bugs.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once both stations were online and transmitting the second issue of the day appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Receiver Overload&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a problem I was vaguely aware of but figured it would not be an issue due
to working low power and working different bands. Facing my mistake head on I quickly
determined I could operate 40 meters with no impact to &lt;code&gt;N7DEV&lt;/code&gt; on 10.
With that solved the only thing left was to await the official start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-here-we-go&#34;&gt;And here we go.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;N7DEV&lt;/code&gt; brought some excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://tikicentral.com/viewtopic.php?topic_id=45867&#34;&gt;Finkbombs&lt;/a&gt;
to enjoy while the event officially
kicked off. Cheers! Anyone for Tiki Bars on the Air (TBOTA)? Weekly TikiNet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11AM Pacific rolled around and 10 meters was quiet, the band scope showed no activity.
I had feared the band would just not be cooperating today.
In contrast, 40 meters was alive and significantly less crowded than 20.
I decided to keep my station on 40 for the remainder of the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a few contacts in the log on 40 we started to hear 10 wake up. A fairly local
station (&lt;code&gt;KJ7JKJ&lt;/code&gt;) located in nearby Las Vegas was calling CQ but not for Field Day&amp;hellip;&lt;br&gt;
We&amp;rsquo;ll take it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short while later Victor Echo stations are heard and &lt;code&gt;VE7NOR&lt;/code&gt; is the first 10m Field Day QSO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back on 40 we&amp;rsquo;ve added &lt;code&gt;UT&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;ID&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;AZ&lt;/code&gt; to the log and multiple sub-sections of &lt;code&gt;CA&lt;/code&gt;.
This is going well&amp;hellip;then &lt;em&gt;we hear it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;This is November Seven Oscar Sierra, Microsoft Radio Club. CQ Field Day.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dropping my station mic and immediately heading over to the 10 meter station to throw out my call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N7OS&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;K7JSX we are 3 Alpha Western Washington&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;K7JSX&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;N7OS we are 2B NV and big fans of Windows Vista on this end.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had just worked &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microhams.com/&#34;&gt;MicroHAMS&lt;/a&gt;, a club comprised of
Microsoft Employees. It may not be the furthest contact but given the opportunity for
long time Windows SysAdmins to express gratitude directly to a Microsoft employee,
it will absolutely be the most memorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-stats&#34;&gt;Some stats.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had intended to work more on 17 meters and at least attempt
80 meters but these goals were just not in the cards this year.
Something to attempt for Winter Field Day&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the final counts&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Band&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;QSO Count&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;40m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;43 SSB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;20m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;8 SSB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;10m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;24 SSB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I do not gauge the success of the operation by these numbers, this marks
a &lt;strong&gt;108%&lt;/strong&gt; increase in total QSOs from the previous year and I
consider that progress a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons Learned.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We quickly learned a few things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bandpass filters.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This is simply a requirement for operating transmitters in such
close proximity. I had not understood this as a viable concern
while preparing for the event. Even QRP power levels are more
than enough to overload the receiver of a nearby station.
A collection of bandpass filters will need to sourced before
attempting multiple transmitters again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contingency Antennas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The original idea of running a vertical for 10 meters failed
due to my misunderstanding of the Chameleon CHA-BV radial system.
I had falsely assumed only the whip section needed to be tuned but
after consulting the manual after the even the radial sections
required substantial shortening. While the end-fed stepped
in to save the day it was not originally my intention to
bring it along. Always bring alternates!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;until-next-time&#34;&gt;Until next time&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the on-air chaos that is Field Day, I look forward to participating again the in the future.
It not only serves as a operating exercise but also the opportunity to share it with friends
and get outside.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventures in RFI</title>
      <link>https://k7jsx.net/posts/adventures-in-rfi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 11:29:24 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://k7jsx.net/posts/adventures-in-rfi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;rfi-in-my-shack---its-more-likely-than-you-think&#34;&gt;RFI? In my shack? - It&amp;rsquo;s more likely than you think.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFI is something I was introduced to very early on while operating end-fed antennas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is my USB connection to the radio dropping as soon as it goes into TX? &lt;strong&gt;RFI&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Why does my waterfall just display noise when I connect it to USB? &lt;strong&gt;RFI&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Why does my noise floor jump to S9 when a new appliance arrives in the house? &lt;strong&gt;RFI!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;rfi-in-my-shack---its-more-likely-than-you-think&#34;&gt;RFI? In my shack? - It&amp;rsquo;s more likely than you think.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RFI is something I was introduced to very early on while operating end-fed antennas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is my USB connection to the radio dropping as soon as it goes into TX? &lt;strong&gt;RFI&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Why does my waterfall just display noise when I connect it to USB? &lt;strong&gt;RFI&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Why does my noise floor jump to S9 when a new appliance arrives in the house? &lt;strong&gt;RFI!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so how do we solve this problem? Suppression with &lt;a href=&#34;https://k7jsx.net/reference/#ferrites&#34;&gt;Ferrites!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some scenarios it&amp;rsquo;s easy to identify the source of the problem&amp;hellip; &lt;br&gt;
Did something just get plugged in? &lt;br&gt;
Did something just turn on? &lt;br&gt;
Bingo! You found it. &lt;br&gt;
Throw an appropriately sized ferrite on it and move on with life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the source of the noise is not apparent it&amp;rsquo;s critical to be methodical and
scientific to reliably detect and suppress it. Learn from my mistakes.
It may be emitting from something you control in your own home
or something external.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;case-study&#34;&gt;Case Study&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-challenger-approaches&#34;&gt;A challenger approaches&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently brought a new appliance into my home, a Samsung Refrigerator.
It brought with it two different types of ice, a neat auto-refilling water pitcher,
and &lt;strong&gt;S9 noise on bands 20m-10m&lt;/strong&gt;. I knew something was wrong
but not how to effectively resolve. How do I stop something from making
noise when all I can see is the power cord? Do I lose access to operate my
favorite HF bands from home for the foreseeable future or void a warranty?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I quickly determined access to those bands had more value than the non-returnable
refrigerator now sitting in my kitchen. Let&amp;rsquo;s see what we can do&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;plan-a---seek-an-accepted-solution&#34;&gt;Plan A - Seek an accepted solution.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With little experience in this area I turned to searching the internet. This
turned up &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/amateurradio/comments/1b5177y/samsung_fridge_rfi/&#34;&gt;a reddit post&lt;/a&gt;
referencing the specific brand, some steps already taken and a potential &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/amateurradio/comments/1bmpr4b/solution_to_samsung_fridge_rfi/&#34;&gt;solution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perfect. Lets give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I selected a comparable part that would fit my new source of noise, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.digikey.com/en/products/detail/schurter-inc/5500-2044/642121&#34;&gt;SCHURTER INC / 5500.2044&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once installed the noise dropped but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t completely gone&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;ruh roh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;plan-b---flounder&#34;&gt;Plan B - Flounder.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enlisting the help of my trusty Elecraft Kx2 and a small HT antenna I attempted to locate what parts of the
fridge were actually radiating. Using the Kx2 much like a metal detecting wand,
I quickly determined most of the noise was emitting from the
door and the rear panel. Anywhere in the vicinity of the fridge the Kx2
registered &lt;strong&gt;S5&lt;/strong&gt; noise. Not great, not terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, what do we do? Ferrite anything we can reach. &lt;br&gt;
Ferrites on the cables leaving the control board. &lt;br&gt;
Ferrites on the cables leading to the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this step completed the Kx2 no longer had a registration on the S-meter when
near the fridge! Progress! Let&amp;rsquo;s check the main QTH antenna&amp;hellip;&lt;strong&gt;still S5&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point I doubted the fridge was involved. Time to try something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;plan-c---cut-the-power&#34;&gt;Plan C - &lt;em&gt;Cut the power.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To figure out where this noise was really coming from I powered down everything in
the house and flipped the main service breaker.
Remember when I said we needed to be scientific? Now&amp;rsquo;s the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Remember kids, the only difference between Science and screwing around is writing it down.&amp;rdquo; -Adam Savage&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these words of wisdom in mind lets write it down:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Band&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Noise Level&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;10m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;S1 to S2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;15m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;S1 to S2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;17m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;S3 (?)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;20m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;S4 (!)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;30m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;S1 to S2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;40m&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;S2 to S3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our noise floor was higher than we realized on 17 and 20 but there is room for improvement on all bands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flipping breakers on one-by-one and checking the waterfall and S meter I located multiple sources of noise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple AirPort Express. &lt;em&gt;Disconnected&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Chromecast USB power supply. &lt;em&gt;Trashed&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bedside table USB charge port. &lt;em&gt;Trashed&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No-name USB charger used to power my Meshtastic node. &lt;em&gt;Tuh-rashed!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Once power was completely restored I noted readings on all bands were very close to
the readings when the power was completely removed!&lt;/strong&gt; Perfect!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The HVAC air handler and outdoor compressor added &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; noise
but not enough to warrant touching them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;success&#34;&gt;Success.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we solved our noise problems but what did we learn?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to know your local noise level&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;br&gt;
Without these base readings you may waste time attempting to solve problems outside your control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to be methodical.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Formulate a plan, enact the plan then evaluate results. &lt;br&gt;
This is the quickest way to success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s some resources I reviewed during this whole process. &lt;br&gt;
I hope they also help you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HRCC - &lt;em&gt;WE are killing the amateur radio bands, and here is how to fix it.&lt;/em&gt; - (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QQzmMOJvFfc&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reddit - &lt;em&gt;Samsung Fridge RFI&lt;/em&gt; - (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/amateurradio/comments/1bmpr4b/solution_to_samsung_fridge_rfi/&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QRM.guru - (&lt;a href=&#34;https://qrm.guru/&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
